So, imagine that you take a 19-hour, very long drive
تخيل أنك تذهب في رحلة طويلة تستغرق فيها 19 ساعة بالسيارة،
to Disney World,
إلى عالم ديزني،
with two kids in the back seat.
مع طفلين في المقعد الخلفي.
And 15 minutes into this 19-hour trip,
وبعد 15 دقيقة من بدء رحلة الـ 19 ساعة،
the immutable laws of nature dictate
بسبب طبيعتنا البشرية
that you get the question:
يسألني أطفالي:
"Are we there yet?"
"هل وصلنا بعد؟!"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So you answer this question a hundred more times, easily,
وتجيب على هذا السؤال مئة مرة أخرى بكل سهولة
in the negative,
بالنفي،
but you finally arrive.
ولكنك تصل أخيرًا.
You have a wonderful, wonderful, wonderful trip.
لقد كانت رحلة رائعة، رائعة، رائعة.
You drive 19 long hours back home.
ثم تقود لمدة 19 ساعة أخرى في طريق العودة.
And when you get there,
وعندما تصل هناك،
the police are waiting on you.
تجد الشرطة في انتظارك.
They accuse you of committing a crime
يتهمونك بارتكاب جريمة
that occurred while you were away in Florida.
حدثت أثناء وجودك في فلوريدا.
You tell anybody and everybody who will listen,
وتخبر أي شخص وكل شخص من الممكن أن يسمع لك،
"I didn't do it!
"أنا لم أفعل ذلك !
I couldn't have done it!
من المستحيل أن أكون من فعلها
I was hanging out with Mickey and Minnie and my kids!"
كنت ألهو مع ميكي وميني (شخصيات كرتونية) وأطفالي!"
But no one believes you.
ولكن لا يصدقك أحد.
Ultimately, you're arrested,
وفي النهاية، يتم القبض عليك،
you're tried,
تُحاكم،
you're convicted
تثبت إدانتك
and you are sentenced.
ويحكم عليك.
And you spend 25 years in jail,
ومن ثم تقضي 25 سنة في السجن،
until someone comes along and proves --
حتى يأتي شخص ما ويثبت ـ ـ
has the evidence to prove --
لديه أدلة تثبت ـ ـ
that you actually were in Florida
أنك فعلًا كنت في فلوريدا
when this crime was committed.
عندما اُرتكبت تلك الجريمة.
So.
لذا.
So, I'm a Harvard Law professor,
أنا أستاذ قانون في جامعة هارفارد،
and the last several years, I have worked on
قد عملتُ خلال السنوات العديدة الماضية
winning the release of innocent people
على الفوز بإطلاق سراح أناس أبرياء
who've been wrongfully convicted --
أدينوا ظلمًا --
people like Jonathan Fleming,
أشخاص مثل جوناثان فليمينغ،
who spent 24 years, eight months in jail
والذي قضى 24 سنة وثمانية أشهر في السجن
for a murder that was committed in Brooklyn, New York,
عن جريمة قتل اُرتكبت في بروكلن، نيويورك،
while he was in Disney World
بينما كان في عالم ديزني
with his kids.
مع أطفاله.
How do we know this?
كيف عرفنا ذلك؟
Because when he was arrested,
لأنه عندما ألقي القبض عليه،
among his property in his back pocket
بين ممتلكاته في جيبه الخلفي
was a receipt --
كان هناك إيصالًا--
time-stamped receipt
إيصالًا مختومًا بالوقت
that showed that he was in Disney World.
الذي بيَّن أنه كان في عالم ديزني.
That receipt was put in the police file,
وقد وُضع هذا الإيصال في ملف الشرطة،
a copy of it was put in the prosecutor's file,
ووُضعت نسخة منه في ملف المدعي العام،
and they never gave it to his public defender.
ولم يعطوها أبدًا إلى محاميه.
In fact, nobody even knew it was there.
في الواقع، لم يكن أحد يعرف أنها موجودة.
It just sat there for 20-some-odd years.
فقط وضعت هناك لحوالي 20 عامًا.
My team looked through the file, and we found it,
فتش فريقي في الملف ووجدناها،
did the rest of the investigation,
وأكملنا بقية التحقيق،
and figured out someone else committed the crime.
واكتشفنا أن شخصًا آخر ارتكب الجريمة.
Mr. Fleming was in Disney World,
بينما كان سيد فليمينغ في عالم ديزني.
and he is now released.
وقد أُطلق سراحه الآن.
Let me give you a little bit of context.
اسمحوا لي أن أخبركم القليل في هذا الصدد.
So about three years ago, I got a call from the Brooklyn District Attorney.
قبل ثلاث سنوات، تلقيت اتصالًا من المدعي العام في بروكلين.
He asked whether I'd be interested in designing a program
يسألني إن كنتُ مهتمًا في تصميم برنامج
called a "conviction review unit."
يدعى "وحدة مراجعة الإدانة"،
So I said yes.
فقلتُ نعم.
A conviction review unit is essentially a unit in a prosecutor's office
وحدة مراجعة الإدانة هي في الأساس وحدة في مكتب المدعي العام
where prosecutors look at their past cases
حيث ينظر المدعون العامون في قضاياهم السابقة
to determine whether or not they made mistakes.
لتحديد إذا ما كانوا قد ارتكبوا أخطاء أو لا.
Over the course of the first year,
وعلى مدار السنة الأولى،
we found about 13 wrongful convictions,
وجدنا حوالي 13 إدانة خاطئة،
people having been in jail for decades,
لأُناس قضوا عقودًا في السجن،
and we released all of them.
وأطلقنا سراحهم جميعًا.
It was the most in New York history.
وكانت هذه عملية إطلاق السراح الأكبر في تاريخ نيويورك.
The program is still going on,
لا يزال البرنامج مستمرًا،
and they're up to 21 releases now --
والآن قد وصل عدد من تم إطلاق سراحهم إلى 21 --
21 people who spent significant time behind bars.
21 شخصًا قضوا وقتًا طويلًا وراء القضبان.
So let me tell you about a couple other of the men and women
لذلك اسمحوا لي أن أخبركم عن اثنين آخرين من الرجال والنساء
that I interacted with in the course of this program.
الذين تفاعلت معهم على مدار البرنامج.
One name is Roger Logan.
شخص اسمه روجر لوغان.
Mr. Logan had been in jail 17 years
قضى السيد لوغان 17 سنة في السجن
and wrote me a letter.
وقد كتب لي رسالة.
It was a simple letter; it basically said,
كانت الرسالة بسيطة، قال فيها،
"Professor Sullivan, I'm innocent. I've been framed.
"أستاذ سوليفان، أنا بريء، لقد تم تلفيق تهمة لي.
Can you look at my case?"
هل يمكنك النظر في قضيتي؟"
At first blush, the case seemed like it was open and shut,
للوهلة الأولى، يبدو أن القضية قد فُتحت وأُغلقت،
but my research had shown
ولكن بحثى أظهر
that single-witness identification cases
أن قضايا التعرف ذات الشاهد الواحد
are prone to error.
عرضة للخطأ.
It doesn't mean he was innocent,
هذا لا يعني أنه بريء،
it just means we ought to look a little bit closer at those cases.
بل يعني أنه علينا أن ننظر عن قرب على هذه القضايا،
So we did.
لذا قمنا بذلك.
And the facts were relatively simple.
وكانت الحقائق بسيطة نسبيًا.
The eyewitness said she heard a shot,
شاهد العيان قالت أنها سمعت صوت إطلاق نار،
and she ran to the next building and turned around and looked,
ثم ركضت إلى المبنى، واستدارت وبحثت،
and there was Mr. Logan.
وشاهدت السيد لوغان.
And he was tried and convicted and in jail for 17-some-odd years.
وتم محاكمته وأُدين وسجن لحوالي 17 سنة.
But it was a single-witness case, so we took a look at it.
ولكنها كانت قضية ذات شاهد واحد لذلك دققنا النظر فيها.
I sent some people to the scene, and there was an inconsistency.
أرسلت بعض الأشخاص إلى مسرح الجريمة. ولاحظنا وجود تناقض.
And to put it politely:
ولوصف الأمر بشكل مهذب:
Usain Bolt couldn't have run from where she said she was
يوسين بولت لا يمكنها الركض من المكان الذي قالت أنها كانت فيه
to the other spot.
إلى المكان الآخر.
Right?
أليس كذلك؟
So we knew that wasn't true.
لذلك علمنا أن كلامها غير صحيح.
So it still didn't mean that he didn't do it,
وهذا لا يعني أنه لم يفعلها،
but we knew something was maybe fishy about this witness.
ولكننا علمنا أن هناك شيء مريب حول هذه الشاهدة.
So we looked through the file,
لذا بحثنا في الملف،
a piece of paper in the file had a number on it.
قطعة من الورق في الملف كان عليها رقم،
The number indicated that this witness had a record.
الرقم يشير إلى أن هذه الشاهدة لديها سجل.
We went back through 20 years of non-digitized papers
عدنا 20 عامًا إلى الوراء للبحث في أوراق غير مرقمة
to figure out what this record was about,
لمعرفة عن ماذا كان هذا السجل.
and it turned out -- it turned out --
واتضح أنه -- اتضح
the eyewitness was in jail
أن الشاهدة كانت في السجن
when she said she saw what she saw.
عندما قالت أنها رأت ما رأت.
The man spent 17 years behind bars.
الرجل قضى 17 عامًا خلف القضبان.
The last one is a case about two boys,
القضية الأخيرة كانت لصبيَّيْن،
Willie Stuckey, David McCallum.
ويلي ستاكي، ديفيد ماك كالوم.
They were arrested at 15,
تم اعتقالهم في سن 15،
and their conviction was vacated 29 years later.
وأسقطت إدانتهم بعد 29 سنة.
Now this was a case,
الآن هذه القضية،
once again -- first blush, it looked open and shut.
وكغيرها، من الوهلة الأولى يبدو أنها فتحت وأعيد إغلاقها.
They had confessed.
لقد اعترفا.
But my research showed that juvenile confessions
ولكن أبحاثي أظهرت أن اعتراف القاصر
without a parent present
دون وجود أحد من والديه
are prone to error.
يكون عرضه للخطأ.
The DNA cases proved this several times.
قضايا ال DNA أثبتت ذلك عدة مرات.
So we took a close look.
لذلك نظرنا في القضية.
We looked at the confession,
تمعنا في الاعتراف،
and it turned out,
واتضح أن،
there was something in the confession
هناك شيء غريب فيه
that those boys could not have known.
يبين أن هؤلاء الصبيان لم يعرفوا ما حدث.
The only people who knew it were police and prosecutors.
الوحيدون الذين يعلمونه هم الشرطة والمدّعين العامين،
We knew what really happened;
لقد علمنا ما حدث بالفعل،
someone told them to say this.
شخص ما دفعهم لقول ذلك.
We don't exactly know who,
نحن لا نعلم من بالضبط،
which person did,
الشخص الذي فعل ذلك،
but any rate, the confession was coerced,
ولكن على أي حال، الاعتراف كان بالإكراه،
we determined.
توصلنا إلى ذلك.
We then went back and did forensics
عندها ذهبنا إلى الطب الشرعي
and did a fulsome investigation
وقمنا بتحقيق شامل
and found that two other,
ووجدنا أنها لاثنين آخرين،
much older, different heights, different hairstyle,
أكبر سنًّا، أطوالهما مختلفة، وبتسريحة شعر مختلفة،
two other people committed the crime,
شخصين آخرين ارتكبا الجريمة،
not these two boys.
وليس هذان الصبيان.
I actually went to court that day,
لقد ذهبت إلى المحكمة في ذلك اليوم،
for what's called a "vacatur hearing,"
لحضور ما يسمى "جلسة إبطال الحكم"،
where the conviction is thrown out.
حيث يتم فيها إسقاط الإدانة.
I went to court; I wanted to see
ذهبت إلى المحكمة، لأني أردت أن أرى
Mr. McCallum walk out of there.
السيد ماك كالوم وهو يخرج من هناك.
So I went to court,
لذلك ذهبت إلى المحكمة،
and the judge said something that judges say all the time,
وقال القاضي شيئًا عادةً ما يقوله القضاة،
but this took on a really special meaning.
ولكن هذه المرة كان له معنى خاص.
He looked up after the arguments and said,
نظر إلى الأعلى بعد انتهاء المرافعة، وقال:
"Mr. McCallum,"
" سيد ماك كالوم"
he said five beautiful words:
قال خمس كلمات جميلة:
"You are free to go."
"أنت حر يمكنك أن تذهب".
Can you imagine?
هل يمكنك أن تتخيل؟
After just about 30 years:
بعد حوالي 30 سنة،
"You are free to go."
"أنت حر يمكنك أن تذهب".
And he walked out of that courtroom.
وخرج من قاعة المحكمة.
Unfortunately, his codefendant, Mr. Stuckey,
لسوء الحظ شريكه السيد ستاكي،
didn't get the benefit of that.
لم يستفد من ذلك.
You see, Mr. Stuckey died in prison
لأن السيد ستاكي توفى في السجن
at 34 years old,
في عمر ال34،
and his mother sat at counsel table in his place.
ولقد جلست والدته على طاولة المحامي في مكانه.
I'll never forget this the rest of my life.
لن أنسى هذا أبدًا ما حييت.
She just rocked at the table, saying,
فقط أخذت تهتز وهي تقول:
"I knew my baby didn't do this.
"كنت أعرف أن طفلي لم يفعل ذلك".
And her baby didn't do this.
وطفلها لم يفعل ذلك،
Two other guys did it.
شخصان آخران فعلا ذلك.
If there's anything that we've learned, anything that I've learned,
إذا كان هناك أي شيء تعلمناه، أي شيء تعلمته أنا،
with this conviction integrity work,
خلال عملي في وحدة مراجعة الإدانة،
it's that justice doesn't happen.
فهو أن العدالة لا تحدث بمفردها.
People make justice happen.
الناس هم من يحققون العدالة.
Justice is not a thing that just descends from above
العدالة ليست شيء يهبط من الأعلى
and makes everything right.
ويصحح كل شيء.
If it did, Mr. Stuckey wouldn't have died in prison.
إذا كانت كذلك، لما مات السيد ستاركي في السجن.
Justice is something
العدالة هي شيء
that people of goodwill make happen.
يحققه أصحاب النوايا الحسنة.
Justice is a decision.
العدالة هي قرار.
We make justice happen.
نحن من نحقق العدالة.
You know, the scary thing is,
أتعلمون ما الأمر المخيف،
in each of these three cases I described,
في كل قضية من القضايا الثلاث،
it would have only taken just an extra minute --
كان سيتطلب الأمر دقيقة إضافية فقط --
an extra minute --
دقيقة إضافية --
for someone to look through the file
من شخص ما لينظر في الملف
and find this receipt.
ويجد الإيصال.
Just one -- to look through the file, find the receipt,
فقط واحد -- ينظر في الملف ويجد الإيصال،
give it to the public defender.
يعطيه للمحامي.
It would have taken someone just a minute
كان سيكلف الأمر شخصًا ما دقيقة واحدة فقط
to look at the video confession and say, "That cannot be."
للنظر في فيديو الاعتراف ويقول "لا يمكن أن يكون هذا صحيحًا".
Just a minute.
فقط دقيقة واحدة.
And perhaps Mr. Stuckey would be alive today.
ولربما كان السيد ستاكي على قيد الحياة اليوم.
It reminds me of one of my favorite poems.
وهذا يذكرني بواحدة من قصائدي المفضلة.
It's a poem that Benjamin Elijah Mays would always recite,
إنها قصيدة دائمًا ما يسردها بنيامين إليجا ميز،
and he called it "God's Minute."
وأسماها "دقيقة الله"،
And it goes something like this:
وهي تقول شيئًا من هذا القبيل:
"I have only just a minute,
"ليس لدي سوى دقيقة واحدة،
only 60 seconds in it,
بها فقط 60 ثانية،
forced upon me, can't refuse it,
أُجبرتُ عليها، لا يمكنني رفضها،
didn't seek it, didn't choose it.
لم أسعى لها، ولم أختارها،
But it's up to me to use it.
ولكن الأمر متروك لي لأستخدمها،
I must suffer if I lose it, give account if I abuse it.
سأُعاني إذا ما فقدتها وأيضًا إذا أسأت استخدامها.
Just a tiny little minute,
فقط دقيقة صغيرة جدًا
but eternity is in it."
ولكن الخلود فيها".
If I were to charge
إذا كنت سأوجه التهم
each and every one of us,
لكل واحد منا،
I would want to say something like,
لوددت أن أقول شيئًا مثل،
"Every day,
"كل يوم،
every day,
كل يوم،
take just one extra minute
خذ فقط دقيقة واحدة
and do some justice.
وحقق بعض العدالة.
You don't have to --
ليس عليك ---
I mean, some people spend their careers and their lives,
أنا أعني أن هناك أُناس يفنون حياتهم المهنية وأعمارهم،
like public defenders,
مثل المحامين العامين،
doing justice every day.
لتحقيق العدالة كل يوم.
But in your professional lives, whatever you do,
ولكن في حياتك المهنية، مهما كنت تفعل،
take time out
خذ بعض الوقت
to just
فقط
do some justice.
لتحقق بعض العدالة.
Make a colleague feel better.
اجعل زميلًا يشعر بتحسن.
If you hear something that's sexist,
إذا سمعت شيئًا عنصريًا،
don't laugh, speak up.
لا تضحك، خذ موقف.
If someone is down, lift them up,
إذا كان هناك شخص بأزمة، فساعده،
one extra minute each day,
فقط دقيقة واحدة إضافية في كل يوم،
and it'll be a great, great place.
وسوف يصبح المكان رائعًا جدًا.
I want to show you something.
أريد أن أريكم شيئًا.
Now, above me is a picture
الآن، فوقي صورة
of David McCallum.
لديفيد ماك كالوم،
This is the day he was released from prison.
هذا اليوم الذي أطلق سراحه من السجن.
After 30 years, he got to hug a niece
بعد 30 عامًا، تمكن من أن يعانق ابنة أخته
he had never been able to touch before.
التي لم يكن قادرًا على لمسها من قبل.
And I asked him then,
وسألته في وقتها،
I said, "What's the first thing you want to do?"
قلت "ما أول شيء تريد أن تفعله؟"
And he said, "I just want to walk on the sidewalk
وأجابني "أريد فقط أن أمشي على الرصيف
without anybody telling me where to go."
دون أن يخبرني أحد أين أذهب".
Wasn't bitter,
أليس هذا مريرًا.
just wanted to walk on the sidewalk.
فقط يريد أن يمشي على الرصيف.
I spoke to Mr. McCallum about two weeks ago.
لقد تحدثت مع السيد ماك كلوم قبل نحو أسبوعين،
I went to New York.
ذهبت إلى نيويورك،
It was on the two-year anniversary
كانت الذكرى السنوية الثانية
of his release.
لإطلاق سراحه.
And we talked,
وتحدثنا،
we laughed, we hugged, we cried.
ضحكنا، تعانقنا، وبكينا.
And he's doing quite well.
وهو الآن بخير.
And one of the things he said when we met with him
أحد الأشياء التي قالها لي عندما تقابلنا
is that he now has dedicated his life
أنه الآن قد كرس حياته
and his career
وعمله
to ensuring that nobody else is locked up unjustly.
ليتأكد أنه لا يوجد أحد آخر مسجون ظلمًا.
Justice, my friends,
العدالة يا أصدقائي،
is a decision.
هي قرار.
Thank you very much.
شكرًا جزيلًا.